16 chapter 17 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 17 John Manley's Talk The rest of our journey was very
easy, and a little after sunset we reached the house of my master's friend.
We were taken into a clean, snug stable; there was a kind coachman, who made us
very comfortable, and who seemed to think a great deal of James when he heard about the
fire. “There is one thing quite clear, young man,” he said, “your horses know who
they can trust; it is one of the hardest things in the world to get horses out of
a stable when there is either fire or flood. I don't know why they won't come
out, but they won't— —not 1 in 20 We stopped 2 or 3 days at this place
and then returned home. All went well on the journey; we were glad to be in our
own stable again, and John was equally glad to see
us. Before he and James left us for the night James said, “I wonder who is coming
in my place.” “Little Joe Green at the lodge,” said John. “Little Joe Green! why, he's a
child!” “He is 14 and a half,” said Johan But he is such a little
chap!” “Yes, he is small, but he's quick and willing, and kindhearted too, and then he
wishes very much to come, and his father would like it; and I know the master
would like to give him the chance. He said if I thought he would not do he
would look out for a bigger boy; but I said I was quite agreeable to try him
for 6 weeks 6 weeks!” said James; “why it'll be another 6 months before he can be
made of much use! It will make you a deal work,
John.” “Well,” said JN with a laugh, “work and I are very good friends; I never was
afraid of work yet.” “You are a very good man,” said James. “I
wish I might ever be like you.” “I don't often speak for myself,” said
John, “but as you are going away from us into the world to shift for yourself
I'll just tell you how I look on these things. I was just as old as Joseph when
my father and mother died of the fever within 10 days of each other, and left me
and my sister Nelly alone in the world, without a relation we could look
to for help. I was a farmer's boy, not earning enough to keep myself, much less
both of us, and she must have gone to the workhouse but for our mistress (Nelly
calls her her angel, and she has good right to do so). She went and hired a room
for her with old Willow Mallet, and she gave her knitting and needle work to do
when she was able to do it; and when she was ill she sent her dinners and many
nice, comfortable things, and was like a mother to her.
Then the master he took me into the stable under old Norman, the coachman
that was then I'll have my food at the
house and my bed in the loft, and a suit of clothes, and three shillings a week, so
that I could help Nelly. Then there was Norman; he might
have turned around and said at his age he could not be troubled with a raw boy
from the plow tail but he was like a father to me, and took no end of pains
with me. When the old man died some years after I stepped into his place, and now
of course I have top wages, and can lay
by for a rainy day or a sunny day, as it
may happen, and Nelly is as happy as a bird see you see, James I'm not the man
that should turn up his nose at a little
boy and vex a good, kind master. No, no! I shall miss you very much, James, but we
shall pull through, and there's nothing like doing a kindness when is put in
your way, and I'm glad I can do it.” “Then,” said James, “you don't hold
without saying, 'Everybody look after himself, and take care care of number
one'?” “No, indeed,” said John, “where should I and Nelly be if master and mistress and
old Norman had only taken care of number one? Why, she in the workhouse and I hoing
turnips! Where would Black Beauty and Ginger be if you would only thought of
number one? why, roasted to death! No, Jim, no! that is a selfish, heathenish saying,
whoever uses it; and any man who thinks he has nothing to do but take care of
number one, why, it's a pity but what he had been drowned like a kitten or a
puppy before he got his eyes open; that's what I think,” said John, with a very
decided jerk of his head. James laughed at this; but there was
a thickness in his voice when he said, “You have been my best friend except my
mother; I hope you won't forget me.” “No, lad, no!” said John, “and if ever I can
do you a good turn I hope you won't forget
me.” The next day Joe came to the stable to learn all he could before James left.
He learned to sweep the stable, to bring in the straw and hay; he began to clean
the harness, and helped wash the carriage.
As he was quite too short to do anything in the way of grooming Ginger and me,
James taught him upon merry legs for he was to have full charge of him, under JN
He was a nice little bright fellow, and always came whistling to his
work merry legs was a good deal put out at being “mauled about,” as he said, “by boy
who knows nothing;” but toward the end of the second week he told me
confidentially that he thought the boy would turn out well. At last the day came when James had
to leave us; cheerful as he always was, he looked quite downhearted that
morning. “You see,” he said to John I'm leaving a great deal behind; my mother
and Betsy, and you, and a good master and mistress, and then the horses, and my old
Mery legs and the new place there will not be a soul that I shall know. If it
were not that I shall get a higher place, and be able to help my mother better, I
don't think I should have made up my mind to it; it is a real pinch,
John I James, lad that it is; but I should
not think so much of you if you could leave your home for the first time and
not feel it. Cheer up, you'll make friends there; and if you get on well, as I am
sure you will, it will be a fine thing for your mother, and she will be proud
enough that you have got into such a good place as that.”
So John cheered him up, but everyone was sorry to lose James; as for Mery legs he
pined after him for several days, and quite went off his appetite. So John took
him out several mornings for the leading rain when he exercised me, and, trotting
and galloping by my side, got up the little fellow's spirits again, and he was soon all
right. Joe's father would often come in and give a little help, as he understood
the work; and Joe took a great deal of of pains to learn, and John was quite
encouraged about him end of chapter